So, yes,
today's sutra is Samyutta Nikaya Agama
616. And um
And um
that is uh
the um
the Chinese parallel to the famous
simile of the cook.
Um this one is kind of I don't know,
maybe just cuz I'm used to that Pali
sutra. This one seems
This one seems
more descriptive or something, I don't
know. But maybe it's just a novelty cuz
it's written differently or something,
but um
I I I still find it quite useful, so um
that's why I thought we can go through
that. So, it says um
So, it says um
"Thus have I heard.
At one time the Buddha was staying in
Jetagrove Anathapindika's Park in the
country country of Sravasti.
At that time the world honored one said
to the bhikkus,
uh bhikkus, you should take the sign of
your own chitta. Do not let it scatter
outward. Um why is that?
Um why is that?
Well, if a bhikku is foolish,
undiscerning, and unskillful,
not taking the sign of his own chitta,
but taking external external signs
instead, then afterward
then afterward
he declines and gives rise to
obstruction in himself.
It's like a cook who is foolish,
undiscerning, and not skillful
in the uh expedient means, mixing
together the various flavors in service
and of a nourishment for his lord.
Um sour, salty, pungent, bland, they uh
these do not accord with his lord's
wishes, but he's unable to well grasp
what his lord delights in. Sour, salty,
pungent, bland, to harmonize the various
flavors. He cannot closely attend upon
his lord at his side, managing what is
needed, listening to what he desires,
skillfully grasping his mind, his
chitta, but instead use his own ideas in
blending the various flavors to serve
his lord.
So, what does that remind you of?
what does that remind you of?
If this doesn't accord with his lord's
wish wishes, the lord is displeased.
Being displeased, he grants him neither
rank nor reward, nor does he hold
affection for him. So, it's kind of
um guesswork, basically. He just has his
ideas, his preferences that then he just
kind of hopes
would work out for the king.
Uh so, it's a hit or miss, but even when
it's a hit, he doesn't know why it is a
hit. And when it's a miss, he doesn't know
And when it's a miss, he doesn't know
why it's a miss.
Because, again, he's just locked in his
own um projections. um projections.
Um
So, um the foolish bhikkhu is the same.
Says, "Undiscerning and unskillful,
dwelling in the um contemplation of the
body within the body, he's unable to
remove and cut off the higher
afflictions, unable to gather and take
hold of his own chitta,
uh likewise unable to attain inward
quieted quietude of chitta, unable to
attain supreme right mindfulness, right
clear knowing, likewise unable to attain
the four kinds of higher chitta states,
the pleasant abiding, and the secure
nirvana not previously attained.
In other words, he cannot
develop his mind uh sufficiently to the
extent necessary for the nirvana.
Nirvana. So, this is called a bhikkhu who is
So, this is called a bhikkhu who is
foolish, undiscerning, unskillful,
unable to skillfully gather the inner
sign of chitta while taking on external
signs, thereby giving rise to
obstructions in himself. So, that's
We'll address all these little these
subtle points, but you can see
the obstructions do not arise cuz you
perceive things by sight, sound, smell,
taste, touches.
The obstructions arise because you're
unable to skillfully gather the chitta
internally. In other words, you're
unable to maintain the context, uh
contain the animal, hence these things
obstruct you.
In and of themselves, they're not
obstructions. Obstructions come from um
undeveloped cheetah.
So, on the other hand, if there is a
bhikkhu who is wise, intelligent,
eloquent, skillful in expedient means,
having first taken the inner sign of
cheetah, afterward taking external
signs, then at a later time, he never
declines, nor gives rise to obstruction
himself. It's like a cook who is wise,
It's like a cook who is wise,
intelligent, eloquent, and skillful in
expedient means, serving and nourishing
his lord, uh able to harmonize the
various flavors,
well grasping the sign of what his lord
delights in, harm- harmonizing the
various flavors in accordance with his
mind. Uh listening to the flavors his lord
Uh listening to the flavors his lord
desires, he repeatedly serves them up.
Um and once the lord is pleased, he will
certainly receive rank,
uh emolument, and affection. His star of
fortune grows even greater. In other
words, he'll be rewarded for his
efforts. Um
Um
and same goes for the bhikkhu.
So, correctly dwelling in contemplation of
correctly dwelling in contemplation of
the body within the body, he cuts off
the higher afflictions, skillfully
gathers his cheetah, inwardly stills the
cheetah, possesses right mindfulness, clear
possesses right mindfulness, clear
knowing,
attains the four higher
um
cheetah states, the pleasant abiding in
this very life, attains the secure
nirvana previously unattained.
So, this is called a bhikkhu who is
eloquent, skillful in expedient means,
and so on.
And goes the same for the contemplation
of feeling, mind, and phenomena. So, the
four satipatthanas, obviously.
Um
so the bhikkhus rejoiced in the Buddha's
words. Uh
Uh
so the main like um
the main point really, main
[clears throat] points from the sutta is
just like the the the the core, like in
the Pali, is uh
seeing the signs of your own chitta. We
we spoke about it many times.
Uh the suttas mention it
um as a prerequisite to sotapatti,
which uh
also has its own prerequisite, seeing
the sign of the mind was uh conditioned
upon dwelling in seclusion,
but not just some like a mechanical
physical isolation,
but the actual true viveka, internal
viveka, internal seclusion, which is
uh seclusion from lust,
lustful intentions, let alone lustful
acts, uh aversion, um intentions of ill will,
uh aversion, um intentions of ill will,
let alone, you know, acts of anger and
so on. And uh even the delusion,
obviously, the distraction and so on.
So, internally
means you would have had to be secluded
from those things sufficiently enough,
even if you're not necessarily
uh able to abide in the physical
seclusion, though of course physical
seclusion help can help and always helps
these things.
So, those are the prerequisite for
seeing the signs of the mind. But,
you know, chittanimitta as can be
as often
um heard and read about can also become
a thing that's sort of mystified as
well, because people try to wrap their
head around it, you know, what's
chittanimitta, how to see my signs of
the mind, which is the prerequisite for
sotapatti, and so on.
So, then it's kind of, you know, gets
equated with meditation experiences,
visions, and whatnot. But,
uh that's really not what the sutta
describe, neither the Agama parallel nor
the actual Pali. It's really just um
something that you can see if you know
where to look. It's not like hidden
behind a veil of ignorance that you just
need to through some, you know, magical
absorption kind of wake up to.
It's basically if the mind is obstructed
as the sutra says it's because of your
doing. It's because you're foolish,
you're incompetent, you don't know what
to pay attention to, you're ignoring
what how king reacts and what he does
and just serve your own preferences on
top of it and they're absolutely
convinced and locked in those ideas.
That's why you don't see your own mind.
Uh so
like the first question
that I posted um
was uh was pretty much like um
how to see.
How how how like do I see signs of of my
mind? You can ask yourself that
question. Um and if the answer is no
Um and if the answer is no
why not?
As I said there is no any external
condition that's preventing you from seeing the
that's preventing you from seeing the
internal signs of your chitta as the
sutra says.
External signs, external conditions
remain unchanged. So they play no part
in you not seeing the signs of the
chitta. What does?
Cuz there has to be a reason for
obstruction. It can't be oh I'm doing
everything right
but I'm not still seeing the signs of my
mind. No. If you're doing everything right
No. If you're doing everything right
there would be no obstructions that are
obstructing your own mind so you would
be seeing the signs of it. The
indications, the characteristics and so
on. So
ask yourself do I see the signs of my
mind? And the answer is no, why not?
Like again
let that question sink in.
What is now stopping me from seeing the
internal characteristics of my own wild animal?
Like what is the
what is the convergence point?
What is a say
like you could say, you know, seclusion
necessary, withdrawal from unwholesome
states, withdrawal from centrality,
withdrawal from ill will, withdrawal
from distraction, withdrawal from
hindrances. What do all these things have in common?
In a sense, what do
what is the main carrier, let's put it
that way, of all those things, of all
these obstructive states?
What defines obstruction as obstruction
and non-obstruction as non-obstruction?
Pretty much what is a single factor
because of which you're not seeing the
signs of your mind yet.
And the answer is it's
uh your intention.
It's cetana.
And uh even linguistically speaking,
citta and cetana carries that
connection. Uh citta is a as a sort of a um
Uh citta is a as a sort of a um
say you could say it accumulated
horizon. And cetana would be the expression of
And cetana would be the expression of
it.
So,
you start by your own intentions being
driven by ignorance, by hindrances, by
aversion, by greed, by lust, by acts
out, by body, by speech, by mind.
Then you come across the Dhamma, you
learn it rightly, you start to actually
train in virtue, and so on.
And it's like all of that, the sole
purpose of that is to well, first
reduce, then contain, and prevent the
expressions of corrupted citta, of the
wild animal,
as I often compare it.
But that in and of itself, like
abstaining from certain behaviors,
as necessary as it is
uh
in and of itself will not necessarily
uh be able to address
the mental uh aspect of those
intentions. So, that's what's missing for people
So, that's what's missing for people
that say are keeping the precepts
training rightly but still not being
sotapanna. Because on the
Because on the
level of these uh like mental layers
the unwholesome intentions are still not
sufficiently seen, sufficiently
restrained. They are still entertained and accepted.
At least mentally. Maybe you don't say
anything bad. Maybe you don't do
anything by uh by the body, but mentally
when those intentions present
themselves, you do take them up.
You do accept them. You do allow them to
to to to to to occupy you, to
proliferate. So, the single factor for somebody not
So, the single factor for somebody not
being a sotapanna is not uh
having fully sufficiently uh contained,
endured rightly, and eventually uprooted
the or seen beyond the roots of the
unwholesome intentions.
And consequently
that's how you would do it.
So
you want to
see the signs of the mind so that you
can you know understand the nature of
dukkha and four noble truths and be a
sotapanna well
the entire training, everything that
you've been doing so far and you're
planning to do pretty much
needs to be leading up to the point of
recognizing the unwholesome intentions
even on the mental level.
And that's that's the whole, you know,
so many talks in so many other talks
where I often talk about yeah, you know,
like you can as I said precepts are
necessary, virtue is necessary, sense
restraint is necessary, but
you can adhere to it. You can take it on
and kind of
get used to it and really never break
the precepts for 100 years.
But at the same time,
never allow those same principles of
precepts and sensory strength to come
too close on those mental levels.
There is a bit much. So, you tolerate it
there. You allow it there. You engage
with it there, but you never let it go
too far.
Yeah, it's not good enough. If your goal
is right view, that's not good enough.
So, that's why the measure of uh
suitable intentions, skillful
intentions, or unskillful that obstruct
and skillful that don't obstruct
is by your own presently enduring
intention. It's not by your views or
ideas or how you think things should be.
And that's kind of that second part
where it says
uh the foolish cook has his own ideas
what to do.
But he has no reference point.
And most people's Buddhist practice is
that today.
You know, mechanical techniques,
absorption methods, I don't know, squint
3 ft in front of your eye for 3 minutes
before you like like these random
things, random observances, random
exercises, body scanning and stuff.
body scanning and stuff.
How does that relate
to the actual, you know, cheetah, the
king in terms of
which direction is it sending it the
animal? What message is it Wait, you
have no idea.
Cuz you don't even see the king.
Like king's mind, king's preferences do
not exist for the foolish person. He or
he's been told he has to serve the meal
and he serves it according to his own
concocted ideas, theory,
um you know, traditional authority,
whatever he chose to use to justify. All
of that results in he himself not seeing
his own intentions.
And that's why he's never going to see
the king and never be able to actually
address it rightly and recognize, "Oh,
hold on. When I attend to these things,
when I intend them, act out,
this is the result of my cheetah."
And by the way, it doesn't matter why.
You could say, "Well, the whole the
entire world does this thing, and it's
not a problem."
And that might be objectively true,
but it's not true for you in terms of
your practice and where the values
should be.
Because for whatever reason, when I do that
for whatever reason, when I do that
thing that the whole world does, my mind
gets enraged, or my mind gets infected
with lust, or my mind gets distracted.
Now, I can say, "Yeah, but, you know,
that's secondary. Really, it's not a
problem because if it's a problem,
the world wouldn't be doing it." No,
that's the wrong reference. That's that
projected idea of a foolish man who
thinks, "I'll be doing this. It doesn't
really matter what my own mind, what the
king is hinting at."
So, that's where you need to the
beginning of like like discernment of
that reference point of your own wild
animal, of your own cheetah, is
you got to start first and foremost
recognizing the pretty much the broader
sense, the contained of your own
intentions. So,
So,
the whole world is doing this. It's not
a problem. Yeah, but why am I doing
that? That's the That's the question you
That's the That's the question you
always need to have at the back of your
mind. Pretty much as an enduring
context. So, whatever you're doing, you're
So, whatever you're doing, you're
looking as to why am I doing this?
And initially, as I said, maybe somebody
new to this, it can be a bit kind of
"Oh, I'm doing this because of this or
because of that." And you fall into
these psychological kind of patterns and
stuff. You'll calm down,
You'll calm down,
but the context will remain of
whatever's done, at the same time you're
looking as to what's my reason for doing
it. Again, not to arrive at some great
Again, not to arrive at some great
revelation, or I'm doing it because of
this or justification for that matter,
but to see whether it's rooted in lust,
aversion, distraction, I delusion,
distraction, I delusion,
or other hindrances, if you want to
approach it through hindrance side.
That's why.
And that's your reference.
And that's how you would become truly
experience the true viveka from
unwholesome states. Not by going on top
of a mountain, which as I said can help,
but in and of itself, it's not going to
do the work for you.
So, the only way to truly seclude
yourself as a prerequisite to see the
signs of your mind,
to the only way to truly seclude
yourself from unwholesome states,
is through discerning your intentions
and not fueling the unwholesome ones,
the obstructive ones.
You do that long enough, you'll be
secluded from all the obstruction. When you're
from all the obstruction. When you're
secluded from all the obstructions, the
prerequisite for seeing the signs of the
mind, dwelling in seclusion, will be
met. Once you start seeing your own mind as
Once you start seeing your own mind as
an independent living entity,
pretty much in the heart of your being,
not a not a theoretical projection, not
a mystical belief or some, you know,
magical hope. No, the actual living
thing. All right there.
All right there.
Like mind within the mind, let's put it
that way.
Like now, whenever you think my mind is
just my mind, that's all you see.
But you discern that your own mind,
whatever idea of my mind I have as my
mind, has its own mind.
has its own mind.
And I have no access to that mind.
I can't decide for it. I just meet it
meet it uh whichever
way basically has changed or arisen for
me. So, that's exactly what Satipatthana
So, that's exactly what Satipatthana
Sutta describes. My He knows mind of
lust as mind of lust. Not he changes
mind of lust into something more
suitable. No, by knowing it for what it is, you
No, by knowing it for what it is, you
see where the line of your effort and
your responsibility is.
By not knowing what it is, where it is,
to what extent it is, by not seeing that
king actually has preferences to what
you're doing, you just be stabbing in
the dark as most people do and just do
this and do that guided by your own
preference of what feels good for you,
not for the king, not for the mind, not
for the chitta, not for the mind within
the mind.
So, if you're secluded enough,
you'll see the signs of that mind within
the mind, an independent mind of your
mind uh sufficiently enough.
uh sufficiently enough.
You see that, you do have a prerequisite
for understanding the nature of dukkha,
cuz that's the root of suffering. That's
the root of craving, which is the root
of suffering.
The mind. The mind is the root of
craving, the mind that you're not
seeing. So, that's why it pretty much somebody
So, that's why it pretty much somebody
who is seeing their mind on account of
sufficiently maintaining, protecting the
context of
uh beneficial intentions and not fueling
the unbeneficial ones, regardless of
what the world,
authority, tradition,
peers, whoever says,
your intention,
the roots of your intention are the
criteria for whether you will be
tolerating it mentally, acting out of it
physically or not.
And uh
yeah, it's also not incidental why why
nobody can just choose to do that kind
of spontaneously. Oh, I'll just
spontaneously ignore the pressure of the
senses, the pressure of the world, the
pressure of the authority, the pressure
of the history of the tradition, and
just stay on this on this level of like,
yeah, but my intention's rooting last,
therefore I won't follow it.
Like, you really need to have a good
reason to stick there.
Um that's why again, the learning and
the right instruction is obviously very
important. You you can't start rightly,
but you can have all the instruction you
want. You can have the Buddha himself
reciting Dhamma for you
50 years if again you are not looking at
the intentions behind your actions,
behind your speech, behind your
thoughts. You're not going to do the work.
So, do I see the signs of my mind? Well,
no, maybe. Well,
why not?
Why not?
What are the unwholesome unwholesome as
in obstructive? They might not be These
intentions might not be
uh overtly kind of coarsely bad, but you
know deep down you know whenever you're
about to do something, say something,
you know where it is rooted.
Whether it's, you know, subtle desire,
subtle restlessness, subtle this, subtle
that. And that needs to be seen
sufficiently enough and recognized and
familiarized with cuz that is pretty
much the gateway
to um discerning the animal.
And that then needs taming and training.
Um
So, yeah, that was kind of the second
question um
um
that that came on the basis of the sutta
was like the foolish cook serves
according to his own and ideas.
It's the same as I said.
Uh oh yeah, you know, I I like to to sit
and do the body scanning
like every every night.
Why? What's the reason? For you specifically. Whatever practice
Whatever practice
you're doing,
why?
What's your reason?
Well, do you see any connection
that it to to to cheta, to the training?
Do you see how it how it translates, how
it relates, how it conveys the messages?
Is there such a such a kind of um
um uh
like a like a field
that's that's that's connected to that,
you know, the the the cheetah and the
inner signs of training.
Or is it like
I don't really know. Cuz I'm told to,
cuz I've been trying and I found it
helpful.
Helpful in what way?
Pacifying you?
Removing the disturbances?
As I said, many things can do that. Does
that make them unobstructive in terms of
seeing the Dhamma?
Because what's the criteria that you
follow when you practice?
Like what's the criteria that the
foolish cook By the way, you're a
foolish cook if you're not seeing your
mind. Everybody starts as a foolish
cook. That's the point. It's not like, "Oh, I
That's the point. It's not like, "Oh, I
did something wrong and I became a
foolish cook." No, everybody starts as a
foolish cook. So, you can't change that.
But, instead of ignoring it, yeah, you
accept it. Okay, hold on. Like the sutta
clearly says, "If I'm not seeing my own
mind, it's cuz I am maintaining the
obstructions of it. I'm foolish in that
regard." Doesn't mean like, "Oh, I'm an
idiot, uh, worthless worthless person or
something." No, no, no, those are too
coarse thing. This is like on the level
of
hold on.
Am I seeing my intentions?
Am I using the criteria of those
intentions for whether I should follow
inclinations to say something, do
something, think something, or not?
Am I just ignoring that?
So, everybody starts as a foolish cook,
but nobody needs to stay a foolish cook. And
nobody needs to stay a foolish cook. And
people won't stay a foolish cook if they
make the effort.
So, whatever practice you're doing,
you need to know why you're doing it.
Like there is no external justification,
external signs that can justify
ignoring the internal context, the
internal counterpart.
Nothing can come in place of that. So,
So,
whatever practice you're doing,
sit down and ask yourself, "Why am I
doing it?
What's the benefit?"
And then whatever answer comes up,
question that.
And same even if say, "If you're not
doing the mindless techniques or body
scanning and stuff like that that I
always criticize."
Say, "Yeah, I'm keeping the precepts and
reading the suttas."
Okay. When you are actually doing those
When you are actually doing those
things, when you're making the effort to
sustain those things, why?
And the reason why you need to ask those
questions because
there's going to be like a like a um
already a lot of uh implicit expectations
a lot of uh implicit expectations
that will remain uncovered.
So, yeah, I'm listening to to Ajahn Amaro
yeah, I'm listening to to Ajahn Amaro
and and you know, I'm not doing as I
said mindless techniques something I'm
keeping the precepts and stuff. Why?
Ooh, mm, I don't know cuz deep down I
expect something will happen. Something
right will happen cuz I found the best
teacher now. It's like, "Well,
as I said, you can find the Buddha
himself. It won't result in what you're hoping to
It won't result in what you're hoping to
result. Why? Because you're maintaining
that gap between
things actually done
in terms of practice by body, speech,
and mind such as not cultivating as I
said the bad body behavior, verbal
behavior, but then training in the same
principles of the mental behavior.
So, a person wouldn't go as far and then
would adopt the practice through the
external signs, through the talks and
suttas and stuff, but leave that
internal gap where the intentions are,
filled with hope
and expectation
that these external things I'm doing
will bring up chittanimitta and
sotapatti. So, that is not as wrong as say somebody
So, that is not as wrong as say somebody
completely mindlessly just do it
mechanical body scanning without a grain
of thought or self-reflection, but it's
still on the same level.
It's still not going to result
in the right view.
Because the intentions, your own
intentions, your own chetana,
which is always manifested from that
chitta which is a horizon for it so to
speak, remains completely ignored.
It's not like invisible or not seen.
It's just not valued enough to be to to
to be used efficiently as a reference
point. That's the difference. It's not
like, "Oh, my intentions are hidden from
me or something." Even the most
inauthentic person that just lives
perpetually in a state of bad faith,
consumed by centrality, ill will, and
just acting reacting to impulses,
even they
cannot truly obscure their intention at
any given time. That's why deep down
everybody knows
what they're doing and why they're doing
it. They might ignore it, they might
keep the momentum going so that they
never had to stop and look back at it,
but that cannot be covered.
That's just the nature of the mind. You
are paired with the chitta. You're
paired with the animal. You can't You
you can be covering it up all you want.
It's always going to be there right
underneath. So, that's the point. Chitta chetanas,
So, that's the point. Chitta chetanas,
your intentions are not mysteriously
hidden. They you not need to do a new
set of practice to reveal that.
No, they're there. They're seen. They're
engaged with. They're multiplied through
your own reflection and chosen and
stuff. They're just not valued enough as
something to stick to.
So, you have the idea, "Ah, it's not a
big thing."
It's not a big problem. It's just a
thought, you know.
But I'm I'm not going to say anything.
I'm not going to do anything.
But when it comes up that choice, it's
always a choice, by the way.
That's how the you know, multi era of
the first and you know, video used to
translate it, if I remember correctly,
in their early early letters. Well,
they're talking about translating uh
chetana's choice.
Cuz it's always on the level when you
exercise choice and you do exercise
choice, which means there is always uh
self-awareness. You cannot exercise a
choice when you are unaware.
I mean, you can do a choice habitually,
but there is still awareness of the
choice. You're just ignoring it and not
emphasizing it enough.
And I've been talking about it in
previous talks, like recognizing that
choice and sticking to the right one
whenever there is enough self-awareness
to know that oh, that's that choice.
It's not going to be perfect from the
start. You're going to be, you know,
ignoring, falling for it, distracted
from it, and so on.
But if you learn enough, you'll be
catching it more and more, the moments
when you make this choice choices
before you make them and then not make
them. That's the practice. The practice
is not oh, I'm aware of the moment now
and I feel my body and the universe and
the experience as a whole or whatever.
No, no, no, no, no.
The practice is not to make the wrong
choice.
And what's the wrong choice? Well,
anything that obstructs. What is it that
obstructs? Well,
it obstructs the mind if it's rooted in
lust, desire, greed,
aversion, ill will, irritation,
distraction, mindlessness,
laziness, spread it to the hindrances in all sorts
spread it to the hindrances in all sorts
of um
um
synonyms and and whatever works for you.
But that's the point. So, but it also at
the same time, if it's not rooted in
that, you don't need to you don't need to You
you don't need to you don't need to You
can choose it.
There is no problem.
So, initially it can feel like, "Oh, I
have to police everything. That's just
so confining, so restricting."
It is because you don't know where the
line for your responsibility and your
actual doing is.
But, say, you know, you start doing it,
you put up with it,
it becomes more freeing.
Because you realize, "Okay,
if it's not rooted in those things, I
don't need to police it. I don't need to
worry about it. I don't need to be
catching moment to moment so my
mindfulness doesn't slip and whatnot.
I can do it."
And then if the doubt comes up, which it
will initially, you recognize, "Okay,
now I have a choice in regard to the
doubt. Before I wasn't aware of it.
Before whenever hindrance came up, it
would pressure me and I would just get
caught up in this cycle and I couldn't
stop until I was just tired, basically,
and forgot about it. But now I know.
Doesn't matter
what comes up through that animal,
the mind of my mind, what brings up.
My choice in regard to it remains
unchanged. Doesn't get closer, doesn't
go further. Remains at the same level.
That's that door I keep talking about.
Don't open the door. Doesn't matter
what's trying to get in or trying to
pressure you to open it.
And the more you recognize that, the
more confident you become in it. It's
like, "Oh, yeah."
So, any state of mind, and that's again
the Satipatthana done rightly.
Depressed mind as depressed mind.
Again, I'm not accepting the choices
that depressed mind is offering. Elated
mind, distracted mind,
um any state of mind, elevated, doesn't
matter. Fine. I know it is such,
but the recognition of the line of the
choice and the chetana and the intention
remains unchanged, and that's the
gateway, that's my door to basically
training the animal.
Then you have all the other advanced
the actual, you know, uh a mind training
as the suitas describe
which is, you know, those perceptions
uh presented to that mind um
contemplating this sufficiently enough
so that the mind stops resisting, stops
trying to outrun it, stops reacting to
that to them.
But all that can be done once you
actually see the mind, not like Again,
people can people would be doing it in
the same sense a foolish cook gets all
new ideas cuz he came across new new
recipe books, I new suitas, and then
he's just blindly doing this and that,
one week this, another retreat that, no
internal connection and recognition to
how that affects the mind.
So another aspect here, although I kind
of covered all the questions pretty
much, but anyway.
Um
can go quickly through it. So can I
recognize the difference between my
experience of the external objects and
as in, you know, engaging with the
senses and so on, and the underlying
state of mind that is concurrently
enduring in relation to them.
In other words
am I at least able to some extent to not
be completely absorbed in what the the
the senses
um uh offer?
The sense objects and maintain some
notion of the context of the background
in relation to it cuz that's where your
intentions are. You're never going to
see intentions in sight, sound, smell,
taste, touches cuz that's why you're
looking at them, because of the
intentions not seen.
Intentions not seen that are sending you
in the directions of the sense objects.
So the recollection of the body within
the body again
again
how do you do it?
What is the body within the body? What's
the mind within the mind?
Well, we we I answered it obviously.
It's the animal It's the same with the
body. So when you look at the body,
So when you look at the body,
any idea that you have of it, it's not
the actual body.
There is a body within that.
The body that can only be seen
indirectly on account of purifying all of your uh
on account of purifying all of your uh
intentions in relation to that body.
Where are those intentions? Right there.
Like even there and then when you're
asking yourself, there is intention to
do it. So, ask yourself, okay,
why am I asking myself this? Why am I
doing what Ajahn Molly said to do now?
Oh, I have faith or something.
Why? What is it that the aspect that inspires
What is it that the aspect that inspires
faith in me?
Don't just take it for granted. Nothing
should be taken for granted.
Cuz to the extent you take things for
granted, to that extent you have
obscured your own intentions.
Obviously, again,
goes without saying, it's not going to
be perfectly clean overnight. Suddenly,
all intentions are pure.
But, it's a training. It's the effort
that requires repetition and everything
else. So,
you better start doing it.
Like even things that
even things that
yeah, are self-evident. This is true.
Yeah. This is right. Okay, why? If it's right
This is right. Okay, why? If it's right
and if I understand it as right, well,
I'll be at least a sotapanna. So, why am
I not a sotapanna?
And it doesn't matter if you're a
householder.
Like, that's not an excuse either.
Because no amount of household life,
external signs, as I said, can come in
between you and your own intention.
That's your own doing.
So, if your intentions are not pure
enough, because of which you're not
seeing the signs of the mind, because of
which you're not understanding the Four
Noble Truths, and are not sotapanna,
it's your own doing on that level.
Your own choices are still made
made
in a way that's actually obstructing
seeing the animal.
So, start making the right ones and
even if you don't want to become a
sotapanna, you will.
But, it needs to be done on that mental
level, not just okay, I made a choice,
keep the precept and I just blindly
stick to it.
But, mentally, when things come up,
when there's possibility to choose
rightly and say no to such thoughts, say no to
and say no to such thoughts, say no to
such proliferations, I tolerate it. I
don't make those that effort. I just
I know I won't do it by the body or
speech, so this is fine.
That's why like again, the roots remain
infected. So,
So,
So, yeah, they're like when the sutta
talks about, you know, the inner sign
and stuff, it's it's uh it's just what I
mean by context. When I often say you
develop the right context and then you
sustain that context in regard to your
engagement with the world. That's going
to be inevitable. Satan's multi-touches,
things having to do and so on.
Uh but, the context does not need to
suffer. If the context starts to suffer,
then you need to restrain yourself and
pull yourself back until you can
reestablish the context.
Context of well, I will not lose the
sight of my intentions.
I will certainly not give in to the um
to the as I said, the wide basis of like
uh carelessness, lust and so on because
again, it would fuel the mind in the
wrong way and then I would have a lot
more to undo.
Um and just in case, I don't know, for
somebody maybe it's not clear, the
intentions are not these momentary
things that oh, I just missed it now.
Came, I made it to choice. No.
Intention can last for 5 days. If the
choice lasts for 5 days.
Literally, you're abstaining from choice
for 5 days.
That same intention, same state of mind
is there for 5 days.
Whenever you are aware of it, that's
where it's there.
So, what do you do?
Like, why would you be even looking at
the at the momentary movements and changes?
at the momentary movements and changes?
Only because you don't know where the
emphasis is. Only because Again, see
the foolish cook
can kind of tell the king is not
pleased, but still doesn't have a clue
why as to like what has he done right or
wrong or so he's just getting paranoid
about everything he does now.
>> [laughter]
>> So, everything becomes a problem
basically because he doesn't know where
the problem is.
So, let me now just monitor everything,
but you're still monitoring it at a
completely wrong place.
The problem was never in in in in
in things that you can perceive through
your senses. The problem was always in
the intentions.
Your own choices.
So, you have an intention endured for 5
days because you're abstaining from the
choice, but the mind keeps bringing it
back. What do you do?
Do you bear that sense of confinement?
Nagging, weighing down, increasing in
weight. Even saying, "Yeah, I might as well.
Even saying, "Yeah, I might as well.
Like, I shouldn't be thinking about it
for 5 days. It was just a small thing."
So, it's just a small thing.
It's a hassle to think about it. Well,
let me just act out of it.
Let me just psychologically it until I
find a pleasing solution mentally or let
me go and say something if
it was concerning others or let me do
something. Either way, you made a wrong
choice. Either way, you chose to give in
Either way, you chose to give in
to the pressure of the animal, to the
pressure of the untrained mind and did a
random thing as a result of it.
So, if the choice lasts 5 days, what do
you do? Nothing. You still don't make
Well, you do the right abstaining from
the wrong choice.
If the choice then it lasts for 3
months. What do you do? Same.
But 3 months, I have to keep this
ambiguity, this uh
I mean, it will all go away, literally.
This this mental problem and the
pressure would go away if I just go and
talk to that person.
Yes, it would go away.
But what would also go away
is your own mind with it. In other
words, you would obstruct it. Why?
Because for you
doesn't matter if it's not a problem for
that person, doesn't matter if it's not
a problem for the world, doesn't matter
if it's not a problem for any
system belief system you have.
The It's problem for you because it's
rooted in a wrong intention. It's rooted
in restlessness, it's rooted in worry,
it's rooted in hindrances.
So, do you prioritize your ideas of how
things should be and how the world
should operate and how the mind should
be in response, or do you pre pre
prioritize the actual live state of the
king that's telling you
and you don't know why.
So, you're just doing random stuff until
okay, he's pacified now.
So, I don't have to deal with him. No,
no, no. You don't want to be at the
mercy of the animal. You want to train
it. And the only way to train it, the only
And the only way to train it, the only
way to speak to it
is through recognizing the the the the
the level the layer of the the
background where your intentions are and
then not making the wrong ones.
And I always give that example cuz it's
like a kind of a good simple textbook
um
um conveys it well.
Which is like even in the monasteries,
like you know, I don't know how many
times I've seen that.
Like everybody knows, you know, the
suttas sufficiently enough. You know, maybe not
sufficiently enough. You know, maybe not
every monkey is an expert or read them
all, but they know sufficiently enough.
And they certainly know the suttas, you
know, where the Buddha said
like for example, and you shouldn't say
anything out of anger.
Um doesn't matter what it is.
If for you it's rooted in intentional
ill will, you shouldn't say it. Even if
it's the most beneficial thing for the
world. What matters is your intention. What
What matters is your intention. What
matters is your state of mind.
So then they say, "Oh, the monk wouldn't
say until basically the anger has
subsided. Uh if the thing is not beneficial for
Uh if the thing is not beneficial for
both and so on." But the point was
everybody knows that.
But see like okay, you know, nobody will
like you know
nobody will punch or physically attack
anybody in the monastery.
in the monastery.
Nobody will like I mean it might happen,
but say most people wouldn't, you know,
go really far in like an angry speech,
would be able to restrain it.
But now, you know, mentally like hmm
it doesn't seem like a big deal.
Like I know it's a problem.
But yeah, you know, it's okay. So now
say somebody does something annoying,
junior monk does something annoying.
And often you would see like a senior
monk you know, if he's maybe like really
you know, if he's maybe like really
annoyed with it, he wouldn't do anything
there and then. But say next day or two
or three days later
same annoyance by the way, the same
choice, the same chitta
pushing the same agenda on you.
And it's like, you know, 3 days now. 3
days it's been eating me.
What do I do?
Do I find an external justification to
say something or do I say there is no an
external sign that can replace the
internal recognition of the of the
chitta and the nimitta does in the
characteristics. So if that's your value, you wouldn't do
So if that's your value, you wouldn't do
anything. Even if 6 months later that
same annoyance in regard to what
somebody did still there, you're still
not acting out of it.
And it might be, who knows? It might be
month for months, depending on like
depending on the mind of your mind that
you have no say in.
Why is it like this? Why doesn't really
matter, really.
It's irrelevant. So most of the monks
that I remember, most of the people
basically would find one reason or the
other to justify and then say it.
They would not say it through like anger
or something, but it would always be
uh they would make a policy in the
monastery or something or do a Dhamma
talk where it's just about that just to
preemptively address that and basically
which becomes a form of acting out of
that mind because that uncertainty
abstaining from the wrong choice, it's
increasing its weight. I can do it one
day, two days, three days, maybe a week,
but after a while
while it's increasing its weight, it's
kind of decreasing its value. That's how
it seems. Like it's it's not a big deal.
And it's also for the good of the
monastery because what he did was
factually wrong. Other people might do
it and then everything we worked for,
this great Dhamma and and the monastery
we built and inspiration we provide,
everything will go to ruin. That's your
own crazy citta, untrained animal trying
to get you to act.
It will tell you, "Hey, open the gate
for me." And you say, "No, I'm
practicing restraint."
Like, "Oh, okay."
>> [snorts]
>> Well, you know, if you don't open the
gates things can happen out there, you know?
things can happen out there, you know?
Other other other animals can come.
Issues can develop. Are you sure you can
live with that?
>> [snorts]
>> No, yeah, I'm not opening the gate. Oh,
really? You're not opening the gate?
Well, if you're not opening the gates,
we're going to have a problem in here.
Plus the other Okay, okay, okay, I'll
open the gate.
And that's pretty much how it works.
Because if people wouldn't open the gate
regardless of the irrationality kind of
uh irrational
accumulation of the irrational, like
increasingly more irrational scenarios
that your mind is throwing at you, yet
you still don't open the gate, you still
don't make the right choice, you are on
the track to be a sotapanna even if you
don't want to become one.
And that's why I said nobody can
accidentally become a sotapanna cuz
nobody will accidentally
stick to this, which as I said,
completely loses the value of
oh, but it's just it's done for the good
reason. While not doing it, it increases the the
While not doing it, it increases the the
weight that your mind threatens you.
And you just choose to no, I'm still not
going to do it. I'm still not going to
do it.
Nobody will do that accidentally. Only
persons that have understood suta
sufficiently understood the importance of not acting
understood the importance of not acting
out by body, speech, and mind will stick
to it regardless of the storm that
chitta is cooking up trying to scare you
so to open the gate so it can go back to
its wilderness.
So, if somebody is sotapanna, it's cuz
they made the right effort. If
somebody's not sotapanna, it's cuz they
haven't made the right effort. They
might have made all the effort in the
world in all the directions, but not the
right one, not on the right level.
So, I kind of
answered all the questions really.
Yeah, so there's like one practical
thing I received.
So, a person asked, oh, so how should
one practice while working or speaking
um or engaging with others?
Um like, you know, when a person has to
attend to things.
Has to discuss stuff, has to plan, and
so on.
Like, you know, what do I do? In other
words.
Well, everything we just described
really. And in other talks, well, you
protect the context.
So, initially, say
say if your practice was before
revolving around
a bit kind of too much on the cushioned
environment. You know, again, I remember like the
You know, again, I remember like the
places
monasteries around the world where like
even having to like
you know, not by the place, but there
were monks that even having to like
sweep leaves or do stuff. Any form of
like like a physical uh exertion is just too
like a physical uh exertion is just too
disruptive for any mental equilibrium.
And it's kind of worse than a
householder in a way. Householders
don't have that privilege. Don't have
that luxury.
Like, you know, you can be protecting
yourself you want, the mind will be
bombarded with stuff.
So, yeah, you need to withdraw yourself
to some extent.
Uh but the point is
that it comes down to that like
it comes down to that like
as I said
Okay, I might be afraid of doing it
because I'm dependent on the cushioned
environment, but now I learned enough
that those things shouldn't be a
problem. So, how do I engage with them? Well, I
So, how do I engage with them? Well, I
keep an eye on the background. I keep an
eye on the my state of mind, my
intentions. Yes, there might be states of fear and
Yes, there might be states of fear and
anxiety and uncertainty coming up cuz
things are not in my control, you know,
he can say this, she can say that. I'm
accepting the outcomes of that. So, if
somebody says something
that might make my cheetah just jump
quickly I'll focus on not acting out. Doesn't
I'll focus on not acting out. Doesn't
matter if that cheetah hurts then for
next 7 days.
I'll bear that. That's the outcome of
the walking in the right direction.
That's the pretty much how
How would it feel? Imagine, how would it
feel to go with the grain?
How would it feel to go against the
grain? How would it feel to swim with the
How would it feel to swim with the
river?
How would it feel to swim against the
river? Well,
Well,
the Buddha said, "Dhamma goes against
the grain."
You swim basically against the flood.
So, it's going to feel like
uncomfortable. It's going to feel like uh not right. If
It's going to feel like uh not right. If
only I could resolve it mentally. If
only I could find justification. If only
I could, you know, use psychoanalysis to
find why this is so, so to give me a
sense of, 'Oh, now I know why it is, so
it's fine.'"
It doesn't matter. It really doesn't
matter whether it's because something
happened in this life or previous or
nothing really happened.
It's the mind of your own mind.
You don't go worrying around why some
random stranger has a preference of one
kind as opposed to the other. You really
wouldn't You wouldn't worry about it.
So, why do you worry about the
preferences of your own chittas, where
they come from?
You should only worry about whether you
are giving in to them or not.
What they are and how they come to be
absolutely insignificant.
So, when you have to engage with the
world, when you have to engage with the
things,
virtue, sense restraint, and the context
on account of that, and then mental, as
I said, mental choices as much as you
obviously you are aware
at the time. Like, you as in you might
be distracted and so on,
and you might be mentally like accepting
irritation or this or that, but at least
you are recognizing that that is what's
happening. And the broader context is keeping it
And the broader context is keeping it
all together, which is, well, I will not
say anything or do anything by the body
regardless of what's happening to me, so
to speak, how distracted I am and so on.
And if you do fail, then recognize,
"Okay, that was that that that was too
much, at least for now.
So, next time I should be even more
careful before becoming that distracted,
so that then I acted out by body or by
speech." But again,
you can never be
so distracted to become unaware of the
choice. Because you can be distracted,
so you don't see the choice when it
comes up or when it starts coming up.
You only see when it's in front of you,
but it's still a choice.
No amount of greed, aversion, delusion
can make a choice for you.
If choices were to naturally and
automatically follow, you know, what
Abhidhamma and commentaries think, from
greed, aversion, delusion and the states
of mind of that, arahantship would never
be possible.
It would be completely self-perpetuating
thing and you couldn't come in between.
But every single time, cetanā is always
on you. Which means
Which means
indirectly, you are responsible for the
states of your citta in that broadest
sense, not immediately,
but in the broadest sense.
So, kind of related to this question was
another one that I received, which is
so, say you're engaged with a
tasks, duties, work, and so on, um and
things get a bit all unclear and muddy
and you lost your internal or clarity
and peace. Things are disturbed. Like
feels like a jungle. What do you do
there? You know, do you stop, start
counting your breath and stuff?
I mean, again, you might do those little
little things to help you cope,
but you don't need to do any of that.
Why? Because it doesn't matter.
As I said, what state of mind there is.
If it's a jungle, uh there's no clarity
in my mind. This morning everything was
so clear and calm and spacious. Now,
it's just all cluttered. It's all over
the place. What's your intention in
regard to that?
Know that the mind is contained.
But see, not seeing that, you worry
about, "Oh, it's like a jungle. The mind
is cluttered. Dah dah dah." Ah. So, you
don't know the uh cluttered mind as
cluttered mind. You want to change the
cluttered mind cuz it doesn't feel right
because of your ideas or feelings.
You want to change it into something
else that suits your preferences better. It's
that suits your preferences better. It's
like, "No, no, no. You are not
the reference point. The mind is the
reference point." Oh, king doesn't like
that. Well, I'll just keep serving it
until he starts liking it.
Cuz I don't like when he doesn't like
it. So, I'll just force him into it, so to
So, I'll just force him into it, so to
speak. So,
your mind is cluttered, gets busy,
feels like a jungle, unreachable, not as
peaceful, not as comfortable.
That's the state of mind that you know
as such. So, it's like, "Oh, so what do
you do in regard to that?"
Without acting out trying to change it.
So, that's again, that's how immediately
you re-reestablish the context by
recognizing what your intention is in
regard to any state of mind.
So, would it be
would it then
be right to say
that our intention is usually deeply
rooted connected with the feelings and
our need to get rid or have more or
or have more or distract ourself from
it, from the feeling.
Uh well, yeah, yeah, yeah. Like feeling,
perception, intention as the sutra says,
it's inseparable.
So, um
um
you might start with say like more
specific intentions. Well, I want to say
this or do that, but ultimately, yes,
you start going down the pathway of
intentions, it's going to come converge
onto where things are felt.
So, you're going to start to recognize
that simply because something is
felt um um
agreeably,
not even overly pleasant,
you already have intention kind of
towards it to to accept it and so on.
But, those are subtle things, you know, they
those are subtle things, you know, they
can they can become say they can be
discerning in broad strokes. You don't
really need to worry about like like
pinpoint on the level of feeling or
something, because
there are bigger impurities that are
obstructing the chitta way before that,
which is
are there acts by body, speech, and
mind, habits that you're still
tolerating while you know they're rooted
in hindrances?
And then deal with that first. Yeah, the
time will come when you recognize the
subtle leanings of your intention, uh
patiga against the discomfort, uh
leaning towards uh comfort, and so on.
But yes, broadly, everything you do will
fall into these three categories: either
for more pleasure, less pain, or
ignorance of the ignoring, distracting
yourself from neither pleasant nor
unpleasant.
Even though the king is pleased with the
right dishes, it seems that the mind is
at least initially displeased with the
right choices. What would be the
corresponding measure of rightness in
the case of the chitta?
Um
The corresponding of the
Well, it would be basically the absence
of dukkha.
The That's pretty much why the four noble
That's pretty much why the four noble
truths follow.
For the one that sees the signs of the
mind, which follows the one that's been
which follows the one that's been
training rightly in secluding themse-
himself um from um from
internally,
from greed, aversion, distraction, and
the hindrances.
So, that's why it becomes
um that's the that's the verification.
Like, it's not like, as I say, you're
going to have some [laughter] so-
some grand reveal, like parting of the
curtains, and the truth shows itself.
Um
it's going to be like you are unable to
suffer cuz the mind doesn't move in the
way it used to move.
It doesn't latch, it doesn't bite.
It can't, and you know it.
And then it's like, oh, I live like a
lotus in the filth, untouched by it.
So, I live in everything that used to
cause issues and suffering, but
untouched by it.
And so the mind already gets the taste
of that. That's why he's certain
destined for awakening and has
unshakable confidence in the fact that
well, knows the Dharma works.
And even if the whole world comes and
tells you, "No, the Buddha was actually
wrong. And by the way, the sutras we
discovered, turns out somebody wrote
them 400 years ago. And actually there's
a proof and they did the laser scanning
and it was all discovered. It's all
hoax." Well, that was a lucky hoax.
Well, that was a lucky hoax.
Because by doing that, you're untouched
by suffering internally and nobody can
like and it's not even a conviction.
It's not like cuz I convinced myself
I'll never think No, it's literally like
everything it stays the same, yet
animal cannot uh uh make you suffer
anymore. So.
So.
So then you would know that the Dharma
is actually right even if say the
historical Buddha never existed. Which
of course, it's impossible because
otherwise like, you know, who could
accidentally stumble upon the right
instruction unless somebody did it
themselves? But I'm just saying hypothetically
But I'm just saying hypothetically
speaking, even if they prove that all
the sutras are like written by somebody
who's like, "Well, that somebody freed
themselves from suffering."
Because on account of that somebody's
on account of that somebody's
instructions,
I trained my own mind. I prepared the
elephant. It doesn't flinch now and
actually the measure of it is there is
no suffering.
There is peace. And
obviously you value that, but cheetah
value that as well. That's why it's your
duty to train it. Same same like with
the wild animal. It doesn't know what it
is actually good for it.
It wants to go to the wilderness. It
wants to get into fights. It wants to go
and mate. It wants to do this
because it doesn't know
that those things are actually uh
not offering peace, are rooted in
suffering and perpetuation of that
thing. You have to show it otherwise and
when it sees, then it's liberated. Then
you won't have to do anything more.
Uh could you say the hindrances are that
tiny felt need to do something to be at
ease? And we need to restrain and recognize
And we need to restrain and recognize
that felt need as a burden, slavery.
Finally, I have to rescue this way. If
my mind was truly free of hindrances, I
would be at ease regardless of doing x
thing or not. The fact that I feel a
need to do anything to be at ease
in of itself is an obligation, a
slavery. Um Um
Yeah.
Um
That's the I think I spoke about it um
in well, in a number of old talks um as
referring to as as as need to rest, like
arresting. Uh, which is exactly I think what you're
Uh, which is exactly I think what you're
referring to, the ease, which is yeah.
Say uh a presence of doubt.
uh a presence of doubt.
Again, the sole well, the the the the
primary, the fundamental, the root
reason for engaging with it, for being
hindered by it, is cuz you're trying to
get rid of the discomfort of it. That's
why a person who is gripped by the by
the hindrance of doubt would be
revolving around and getting to the
right answer, but then having the need
to repeat it again and again and again
cuz it was never really about the
answer. It's about trying to find the
ease, which is measured by the absence
of discomfort.
So, that is pretty much uh a common
threat to all the hindrances. Same with
sensuality. As I said in other talks,
it's inherently felt as unpleasant,
which is why you seek the desire
uh the the the objects of your desire
and acting out to to to cover that up
and hope to replace it with pleasure and
ease from it. Same ill will.
Like if I don't say it, I'm staying with
the discomfort. I want to be eased from
it, so I'll
maybe I won't do anything physically,
maybe I won't say anything, but mentally
I'll justify it, I'll revolve around it,
I'll make policies, like the example I
gave. So, yeah, yeah.
Um
It's not that that's the only thing that
that's kind of the the the the
hindrances are as I said, they they go
as far
as to
have the intention just for that
mindless ease from the uncomfortable
feeling at the expense of perspective.
at the expense of perspective.
That's also hindrance. But, acting out
physically, verbally, stuff, that is
also hindrance.
So, sometimes people identify just with
these coarse things and things, "Oh, I'm
free from hindrances cuz I'm not doing
anything." It's like, "Are you free from
the need for a gratuitous rest and
ease?" Because making the right choice is
Because making the right choice is
effortless.
Needing to rest from doing it onto these
things means
giving way to the wild animal and
allowing elephant to flinch and move and
exercise some of its wild tendencies and
preferences cuz you can't be bothered.
So, yeah. Hindrances are pretty much, as
I said, the scope of them
goes from one end all the way to the
subtlest kind of
uh
willing choices and acceptances of forms
of lust, aversion, distraction, and
unwholesome states like doubt,
restlessness, and so on.
Like, you have anxiety or worry. You
can't stop the mind from arising like
that. You have the mind of doubt. You
can't stop it.
But, you can certainly never give in to
the tendency to, "Ooh, let me
let me do this or that or give in to it
a bit so it's not as much."
In other words, let me open a gate a bit
and let it go run and then it will come
back. In other words, let me allow its
In other words, let me allow its
wilderness cuz I can't be bothered to
train it fully to the necessary extent.
So, you still remain under the
hindrances.
But, like with all the other aspects of
training, yeah, coarse things need to be addressed
yeah, coarse things need to be addressed
first. So, if you're worrying about the
aspects of rest, not you specifically,
but just generally a person,
"Mm, right, I mustn't rest internally,
context protect." But, then still
tolerate choices of
uh physical uh
acting out of physical lust and verbal
and anger and so on. It's like yeah,
like you you have a bigger fish to fry
first. Then you can see the scope and the
Then you can see the scope and the
subtlety and the depth of hindrances and
address it.
After master, so then could you say
it's the unquestioned mission of this
needs to be solved that is the problem.
The problem is not the phenomenon of
doubt you will by itself. Yeah.
And that's pretty much what we answered
now. The point is
like how the suta says, things like sign
of beauty, sign of ugliness, things
suitable for doubt
um
basically the basis for hindrances are
not what the hindrance is. Trying to
deal with that means not basically
failing to see that you're already
hindered. How are you hindered by
wrongly attending to those things?
What's the
most basic definition of wrongly
attending to something is
thinking that that's a problem when it
actually isn't. That's already a form of
ayoniso manasikara.
So thinking to that there's some extent
this deserves
giving in so to get the ease and
resolution and fixing and so on.
To that extent it's ayoniso manasikara
and as the Buddha said it's the ayoniso
manasikara that makes things that are
basis for hindrances to be the
hindrance, not those things.
Because the one who attends to them
rightly, the sign of beauty remains, the
sign of repulsiveness remains, things
suitable for doubt uh
suitable to lend themselves to doubt
remain. Yet you're beyond hindrances.
So that's why I always go on about, you
know, the whole kind of traditional
common ideas like I must counter and
deal with this or that I must get rid of
it, get rid of it, get rid of it. Think
the opposite, think the opposite. It's
like you you yes, you're not seeing your
mind there. You're just action reaction
basically. Like thoughts come up
Like thoughts come up
I do the opposite. Why?
Instead of just blindly, I do the
opposite cuz Buddhaghosa said so.
No, why am I doing the opposite?
And then you realize, "Oh, cuz I
absolutely hate the feeling of this."
Oh, cuz you're acting out of ill will.
So, how is that going to free you from
hindrance? It's not.
It's not.
So, the record That's why virtue, sense
restraint, the gradual training before
you can even come close to actually
containing the hindrances rightly.
Why? Because when these thoughts present
themselves, they will be pushing these
choices. And yes, you don't welcome, entertain,
And yes, you don't welcome, entertain,
choose, proliferate the thoughts of
those choices,
but you suddenly don't try to like I
must get rid of this state of chitta
altogether cuz that would be rooted in
pure aversion,
pure resistance.
Which means that will hinder you even if
you address every hindrance through your
method methods and managements, it will
continue to hinder you cuz the roots of
your intentions remain unchanged.
So, enacting along with that attitude of
this is a problem keeps giving it
validity, keep making it a problem,
keeps making it a problem.
Uh well, yeah, yeah. Like that's why as
I said just now, learning is important
so that you can shift the emphasis of
your views.
Like you need to learn that that's not a
problem despite your whole being
feeling, "No, that is a problem. If only
I say do this or react that,
I will free myself from the confinement
of this state of mind of this problem."
And you have to go against that
tendency, against that need.
And the only person will do it is the
one that heard
many times that actually, "No, that's
not a problem. Trust me on that. Try
doing it and you'll see it for
yourself." So, literally like a doctor telling you,
So, literally like a doctor telling you,
"Stop eating that. It's harming you."
But you don't see the connection and you
don't trust the doctor and you continue
eating it.
But for whatever like some person might
actually for one reason or the other
choose to okay, I'll trust the doctor
and despite not having any problem with
this food, not any issue with this food,
I will stop eating it cuz he said so
and maybe other symptoms will then show
and I can see for myself that actually
yes, it was a problem. So,
a degree of faith is necessary even when
it comes to this.